<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dishajk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://dishajk.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-19T23:13:46+05:30</updated><id>https://dishajk.github.io/feed.xml</id><subtitle>This site has Disha's portfolio in mathematics outreach and education, her blog, calendar, and contact details, along with curated resources for students, educators, and those navigating mental health challenges. It is a space for learning, connection, and collaboration.</subtitle><author><name>Disha Kuzhively</name><email>dishajk21@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Sick, Stuck, and Thinking</title><link href="https://dishajk.github.io/2024/12/19/Sick-Stuck-and-Thinking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sick, Stuck, and Thinking" /><published>2024-12-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-12-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://dishajk.github.io/2024/12/19/Sick-Stuck-and-Thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dishajk.github.io/2024/12/19/Sick-Stuck-and-Thinking.html"><![CDATA[<p>Writing requires sitting down. Reading a math research paper also requires sitting down. This probably explains why I haven’t managed to do either in the past several months.</p>

<p>I fell ill—very badly this time—and had to see a doctor. The doctor told me it was a viral infection layered on top of my usual allergic rhinitis, which I’ve mostly learned to work around. I was prescribed antibiotics and painkillers in addition to the medicines I already take. I desperately wanted to recover quickly because of a workshop with students where we were going to do tiling (fun math stuff).</p>

<p>When I called a colleague, she could tell from my voice that my excitement was clouding my judgment about my recovery. She suggested I speak to someone else for a second opinion. I did, and during the conversation, I kept saying “Sudoku” when I meant “Rubik’s cube.” You see, both involve squares! The painkillers had clearly left my head loopier than I realized. It was only then that I admitted I was still unwell and not yet ready to return.</p>

<p>How do I “rest”? How do I “take a break”? I remember a psychiatrist asking me this question many years ago, jotting down notes, and prescribing more medication after hearing my answer. For me, taking a break means doing things I haven’t gotten around to in a while.</p>

<p>I can’t sew—sewing requires focus and steady eyes. Crocheting is out too, as most of my works-in-progress need eyes and focus. Instead, I created TikZ graphics to generate aperiodic monotiles of the type Tile(a, b), where a and b are any real non-negative numbers. I even wrote one for the Spectre tile. Spectres are probably already available, but I wanted one where I could customize the curve connecting vertices.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/blogImages/turtle1root2.png" alt="Tile(root(2),1) because why not" /></p>

<p><em>Tile(sqrt(2),1) because why not</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/blogImages/spectre.png" alt="spectre" /></p>

<p><em>spectre</em></p>

<p>Now that I’m writing this down, I realize it’s probably been done before. I should reach out to Smith et al. to check. I also decided to work on a GUI where you can input a and b, and the program generates the monotile. But that kind of work demands a healthy mind—one that doesn’t confuse squares with cubes or Sudoku with Rubik’s cubes.</p>

<p>I watched Fantastic Mr. Fox. I loved it, though I think I would have enjoyed it more if it weren’t for George Clooney’s voice. There’s something about it that makes me feel like he doesn’t care enough. But Mr. Fox does care—maybe not as much as Mrs. Fox, but he does.</p>

<p>I can’t cook—I don’t have the energy for it. The friends I usually turn to in situations like this are out of commission: one broke his leg playing football, and the other is attending a workshop in Chennai. The friends I’d ask to come over? One broke his ankle while drunk on a beach, and the other has left the country.</p>

<p>For now, I’ve been surviving on dosa and toast. I eat the dosa with chutney and toast bread with apple jam I made a while ago. When bedridden, I doomscroll and shitpost. One friend, seeing my misery, gave me ginger tea and ghughuni. The ghughuni brought back so many good memories of Odiya food.</p>

<p>The other reason I can’t cook is the state of my kitchen—the sink is piled high with unwashed dishes, and the floor hasn’t been swept or mopped in a while. I need a clean kitchen to be able to cook. This got me thinking: should I hire a domestic worker? Or maybe buy a vacuum cleaner?</p>

<p>I’ve wanted a Roomba-type vacuum cleaner for a while now—it would even help with Naru’s shedding. But when I checked the price, it was way too high. I don’t get paid enough for that kind of splurge. Dyson makes vacuum cleaners too. Their hair dryers are incredible—I’ve seen the ads. Their vacuum cleaners must be on another level.</p>

<p>Interestingly, my vacuum-cleaner-owning friends are also the ones who have hired domestic workers. When I asked why they have both, they said the machines don’t do a good enough job. Sounds right.</p>

<p>I decided to borrow my house owner’s vacuum cleaner, as I always do. The vacuum cleaner, ladder, and toolbox in our building are communal—it’s definitely serving its price’s worth. If I were to buy a Roomba-type vacuum cleaner, it would sit plugged in my house, with no community use.</p>

<p>The large biryani pots are another set of communal items people in the building lend and borrow—or at least they were back when Arshia lived here and did a lot of cooking and sharing.</p>

<p>Thinking about hiring a domestic worker led me to survey what others in the building pay for cleaning. One respondent confirmed they pay 1.7k per month. That’s poverty wage! That’s terrible. I have a huge rant about this brewing—the cost of labor, what’s fair, and what’s outright exploitative. That’s what I sat down to break apart and write about, but the meds are kicking in. I’ll try again once they wear off.</p>]]></content><author><name>Disha Kuzhively</name><email>dishajk21@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Health" /><category term="Rest" /><category term="ADHD" /><category term="Work-Life Balance" /><category term="Maths" /><category term="Tiling" /><category term="Mental Health" /><category term="Self-Care" /><category term="Reflection" /><category term="Daily Life" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Personal Growth" /><category term="Rants" /><category term="Cooking" /><category term="Domestic Work" /><category term="Community" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Writing requires sitting down. Reading a math research paper also requires sitting down. This probably explains why I haven’t managed to do either in the past several months.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://dishajk.github.io/assets/media/try.svg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://dishajk.github.io/assets/media/try.svg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Train, Hair, and Dental Care</title><link href="https://dishajk.github.io/2024/06/25/Train-Hair-and-Dental-Care.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Train, Hair, and Dental Care" /><published>2024-06-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-06-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://dishajk.github.io/2024/06/25/Train-Hair-and-Dental-Care</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dishajk.github.io/2024/06/25/Train-Hair-and-Dental-Care.html"><![CDATA[<p>I can read on a flight but not on a train. I can’t type what is on my mind; I have to write it down. Too many thoughts make me feel constipated mentally. I am travelling on the Vande Bharat for the first time. It’s a bit more congested compared to the Shatabdi. I prefer the Shatabdi when I make my special trips to Chennai. Why trips to Chennai? As of now, for love and to see my dentist.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/blogImages/IMG_20211021_105635.jpg" alt="notebook, pen, and kami placed on a flight seat tray, and a water bottle in the seat pouch." width="200px" height="auto" />
<img src="/assets/blogImages/IMG_20211021_115933.jpg" alt="Drawing on a notebook featuring three people, one with a walkie-talkie, one with hook-hands, and one with a cup of beverage and an eyepatch." width="200px" height="auto" />
<img src="/assets/blogImages/IMG-20240119-WA0001.jpeg" alt="View from a train window showing railway tracks, trees, and a small structure in the background" width="200px" height="auto" />
<img src="/assets/blogImages/IMG_20240625_061505.jpg" alt="Packet of unibic biscuit, girnar tea pre-mix, stirrer on a blue tray" width="200px" height="auto" /></p>

<p>I have found the best dentist. A colleague from IMSc swore by him. My colleague is old, and older people’s dental issues not the cosmetic dentistry that my age people seek for. Let me know if you want the dentist’s contact information. I also have a good hairstylist in Chennai. She doesn’t suggest changing my hair texture with straightening or keratin treatments. Instead, she talks about the lack of moisture possibly causing my hair fall and asks if I want suggestions. The only time she recommends a product is when I specifically ask for one that does something my current products don’t.</p>

<p>In school and college, I considered straightening my hair, but not anymore, not even for fancy occasions. I have a story about this that I will share soon. Yesterday, I rewatched The Incredibles with my friend. I find Mr. Incredible extremely selfish. Surely, Elastigirl had her dreams and aspirations too. It feels like she got stuck with Dash, Violet, and the house while Mr. Incredible pursued his own goals. Is it only white people who don’t worry about family planning?</p>

<p>Back to my Chennai dentist—it’s a private clinic with reasonable prices, which works for me. I am sort of still in academia and underpaid, I can’t afford the standard places like Clove Dental.</p>

<p>Do you know how to fix the footrest in the Vande Bharat seat? It’s uncomfortable. Should I lend the guy next to me some deodorant from my bag? The tea they served is one of those pre-mixed ones with too much sugar, and I hate it. I prefer the Shatabdi way—the “dip tea.” Vande Bharat feels more congested. Shatabdi has more room, and I can go to the bathroom from my window seat without waking up everyone. However, Vande Bharat has roomier bathrooms and pantry area. Neither seem to have dedicated space for service staff to rest.</p>]]></content><author><name>Disha Kuzhively</name><email>dishajk21@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Travel Experiences" /><category term="Train Travel" /><category term="Vande Bharat Express" /><category term="Shatabdi Express" /><category term="Chennai" /><category term="Personal Reflections" /><category term="Dental Care" /><category term="Hair Care" /><category term="In-Flight Reading" /><category term="Movie Reviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I can read on a flight but not on a train. I can’t type what is on my mind; I have to write it down. Too many thoughts make me feel constipated mentally. I am travelling on the Vande Bharat for the first time. It’s a bit more congested compared to the Shatabdi. I prefer the Shatabdi when I make my special trips to Chennai. Why trips to Chennai? As of now, for love and to see my dentist.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://dishajk.github.io/assets/media/try.svg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://dishajk.github.io/assets/media/try.svg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I Want To Write</title><link href="https://dishajk.github.io/2024/01/03/I-want-to-write.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Want To Write" /><published>2024-01-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-01-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://dishajk.github.io/2024/01/03/I-want-to-write</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dishajk.github.io/2024/01/03/I-want-to-write.html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to write. I want to publish the drafts without worrying about angering people, without worrying about the angry people hurting my career. What’s the worst that can happen? I will lose my job and have no ‘monthly income’. I shouldn’t be scared of that. My friend once pointed out that if that’s my bottom, then it’s not such a bad one because I have been there, and I did pretty well. I monetised all my skills, did every odd job I could get my hands on, and paid my bills on time! In the worst-case scenarios, friends helped. Friends helped a lot.</p>

<p>My friend also says that they will have difficulty helping me if I got in the situation in the first place by saying or doing things I could have avoided. My friend has a point. You see when I call out the bullshit of people in power when their position is threatened even slightly so, they get back at you, and most often, they try to hurt you ‘kith and kin’. In an academic setup, that would be ‘hurting’ your office mates or people you are seen working with. I don’t want to cause myself or people associated with me any trouble. I have, therefore, been quiet. Very, very quiet. I tell myself that I will write it down here and there and publish it when I retire or after I am dead.</p>

<p><img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/defensive_profile.png" alt="The egos of people in positions of power are so fragile and threatened by something as small as a tweet of a person who has barely 36 views." /></p>

<p>When covid happened, I almost died. I regretted things I didn’t say. I regretted not being honest and lying to keep everyone around me comfortable and happy. I decided to start being honest. The first of them was telling my mom that I do not believe in god and will not go to church or read the bible. I think it scares her and worries her that I won’t make it to heaven. She tries to change my mind even today; it’s been more than three years. I don’t think she’ll ever stop trying to bring me back into the folds of church.</p>

<p>Now the second thing- calling out bullshit when I see it. I am not comfortable being a bystander. I have been sick of it. Of course, I know that me calling out shit is not going to change the world. Dare I even hope! The bare minimum it can do is get it out of my head. I intend to do at least that - clear my head. Pretending that things are fine when they are not is exhausting. Maybe after I take stuff out of my head and put them on paper (screen?) I will no longer be expected to put on an act?</p>

<p>I am going to publish before I die.</p>]]></content><author><name>Disha Kuzhively</name><email>dishajk21@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I want to write. I want to publish the drafts without worrying about angering people, without worrying about the angry people hurting my career. What’s the worst that can happen? I will lose my job and have no ‘monthly income’. I shouldn’t be scared of that. My friend once pointed out that if that’s my bottom, then it’s not such a bad one because I have been there, and I did pretty well. I monetised all my skills, did every odd job I could get my hands on, and paid my bills on time! In the worst-case scenarios, friends helped. Friends helped a lot.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://dishajk.github.io/assets/media/try.svg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://dishajk.github.io/assets/media/try.svg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unblocking The Writing Blog</title><link href="https://dishajk.github.io/2023/08/05/unblocking-the-writing-blog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unblocking The Writing Blog" /><published>2023-08-05T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-08-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://dishajk.github.io/2023/08/05/unblocking-the-writing-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dishajk.github.io/2023/08/05/unblocking-the-writing-blog.html"><![CDATA[<p>Experiencing writer’s block is similar to having constipation. Like constipation, it’s frustrating, and you find yourself constantly struggling to overcome it. Indeed, it is not the lack of ideas; it is often because you have too many ideas in your head, much like having too much shit in your tummy when you are constipated.</p>

<p>I have been unable to write for a long time now. It makes work difficult, especially when your work is in the Center for Science Communication and Outreach. Written material is an essential medium of communication. I have also been constantly looking for cures. I asked all people, friends and strangers.</p>

<p>In his memoir <em>Words Without Music</em>, if I remember correctly, Philip Glass talks about how he routinely sets apart time to make music. He only writes music if it comes to him within the specified time. He has disciplined his creativity this way. One of my old project supervisors suggested I try Glass’s method because he noticed my sporadic progress, with bursts of productivity amid longer periods of stagnation.</p>

<p>Neil Gaiman, who is accessible to someone like me on Twitter and Tumbler, has a lot of advice for curing writer’s block. ”If you’re being a perfectionist, don’t be,” he says. Perfectionism is a trait my therapist believes has hindered me from timely submitting job and PhD applications.</p>

<p>Another piece of advice out there is to have external deadlines and expectations. I found myself a co-author for an article on dealing with mental health. However, unlike constipation, writer’s block seems contagious, as we’re yet to make significant progress despite reviewing the initial draft and outline.</p>

<p>Is my block because of my social media use? Numerous articles suggest that excessive social media usage reduces one’s attention span. I need to have my thoughts flow at the same rate as my writing/typing to get it out on the paper/screen. A professor recommended that I record my thoughts and then take notes later. I tried this and discovered that a) I have multiple thought tracks running simultaneously, and b) some of those tracks are faster than my speech.</p>

<p>Buying new stationery has worked when I have an artist’s block and cannot paint or embroider. I shop for a new tube of paint, a brush or, in the case of embroidery, a new thread floss. I bought myself a new pen and ink. I tried out an exercise that a friend recommended. The exercise involves writing whatever comes until you reach a point where your writing speed matches the speed of your thoughts, eventually leading to coherence in your writing. Although this was not a complete success, I managed to write the outline for the mental health article.</p>

<p>I hope that, like constipation, a writing block is temporary. Have you experienced a writing block? If so, did you overcome it? If you did, how did you? Do you have strategies to avoid getting one in the future?</p>

<hr />

<p>This article was originally published in the student-run magazine, <a href="https://commuzinebystudents.wordpress.com/2023/08/05/unblocking-the-writing-block/">Commuzine</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Disha Kuzhively</name><email>dishajk21@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experiencing writer’s block is similar to having constipation. Like constipation, it’s frustrating, and you find yourself constantly struggling to overcome it. Indeed, it is not the lack of ideas; it is often because you have too many ideas in your head, much like having too much shit in your tummy when you are constipated.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://dishajk.github.io/assets/media/try.svg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://dishajk.github.io/assets/media/try.svg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>